Guide to the Connie Kopelov Papers WAG.064
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Connie Kopelov Papers
1942-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kopelov, Connie
Siegel, Phyllis
WAG.064
3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
Connie Kopelov (1926- 2016), a pioneer in both labor and women's education and history, held positions in various labor and labor-related organizations including the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, later the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, the Workers Defense League and the New York Labor History Association. In 1972, Kopelov participated in the New York Trade Union Women's Seminar that led to the 1974 founding conference of the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW). In 1975, Kopelov was elected Vice-President of the newly chartered New York City Chapter of CLUW and continued to hold positions in the organization throughout her life. The collection reflects Kopelov's involvement in labor and women's organizations, most notably her involvement in the New York City Chapter of CLUW, and include correspondence, organizational papers and notes, news clippings, newsletters, leaflets, speeches, photographs, and publications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Connie Kopelov in several donations, beginning in 1987. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1988.006, 1988.011, 1988.013, NPA.1997.025, NPA.2000.246, NPA.2000.319, NPA.2003.019, NPA.2005.034, NPA.2005.044, NPA.2006.057, and NPA.2008.026.
Another donation was made by Phyllis Siegel in 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.159.
One audiocassette tape was found in the repository; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this material is 2015.005.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Connie Kopelov (1926-2016) was born April 14, 1926 in the small industrial town of Kokomo, Indiana, to Russian Jewish immigrant parents. After graduating from Northwestern University in 1947 with a BA in political science, Kopelov worked for the Chicago Council on Foreign Relations, a citizens' educational organization led by Adlai Stevenson and Louise Leonard Wright, whose mission was to encourage internationalism. In 1955, Kopelov left Chicago for New York City, where her political activism and involvement in the labor movement would develop quickly.
Kopelov worked briefly for Morris Novick, who was then working as a media consultant for the Frank Edwards Radio News Program sponsored by the American Federation of Labor. She next worked, until 1957, as Executive Director of the New York City Freedom Agenda Program. The Freedom Agenda forums, which originated with the League of Women Voters, were initiated to explore civil liberties issues in the aftermath of McCarthyism and in particular to generate discussion on the Bill of Rights. In the next phase of her career Kopelov began a long period of dedication to labor education. From 1957 to 1962 she served as Education Representative for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. In 1962, she became the Associate National Education Director for the Amalgamated (later the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union). Kopelov conducted resident leadership institutes and legislative conferences for rank-and-file ACTWU members in various regions of the country. She also wrote legislative and environmental policy newsletters for the union. In 1967, Kopelov took a yearlong leave of absence to accept a Senior Fulbright Fellowship to do research on workers education in Britain. From 1977 to 1979, she served as Director of Education for the National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees (Local 1199). She planned numerous staff development seminars and conferences, and conducted teacher-training programs for Local 1199 throughout the Northeast.
In addition to her labor education work, Kopelov has been a strong feminist voice for working women's issues and women's history. In 1972, Kopelov participated in the New York Trade Union Women's Seminar, a series of seminars for staff and rank-and-file unionists originated by Barbara Wertheimer under Cornell University's New York City labor program. The conference coincided with national discussions on women and labor that led to the formation of Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW). CLUW's mission was to address the specific problems facing women in labor and to offer educational, organizational, communication, and political/legislative components on a national level. Kopelov served on the CLUW National Planning Committee, and, in 1975, she was elected Vice-President of the newly chartered New York City Chapter of CLUW. Along with chairing several committees, Kopelov contributed a host of articles and speeches on women's history topics to CLUW journals, newsletters, and conferences. In 1974, Kopelov chronicled the formation of CLUW in her thesis, "Trade Union Women and Women's Rights," for which she earned a Master's Degree from Goddard College. Kopelov further affirmed her commitment to women's history when she participated as a CLUW representative in the 1979 Institute on Women's History at Sarah Lawrence College. At this conference, the idea for a national Women's History Month took form. In 1981, Kopelov again represented CLUW in the Women's Funding Coalition, envisioned as a "United Way" to fund women's organizations through payroll deductions.
In March 1982, Kopelov joined the staff of the Workers Defense League, an advocacy organization for workers' rights founded in 1936. She directed a number of projects including a Speakers Bureau to disseminate labor history on college campuses, a pioneering unemployment insurance advocacy training course, and an employee rights-on-the-job project. Kopelov designed curricula to train speakers, stewards and organizers and prepared resource materials for participants in job training, immigrant, and adult education programs. Kopelov's later projects include editing the annual Labor History Month calendar of the New York Labor History Association, conducting walking tours of women's labor history in New York City, and contributing articles on women in labor history to a wide range of publications. She was an adjunct lecturer on labor history at Cornell University and New York University.
She has been the recipient of a number of awards and honors, including NYC-NOW's Susan B. Anthony Award and the John Commerford Labor Education Awatrd of the New York Labor History Association.
In 2011, she and her partner Phyllis Siegel were the first same sex couple to be married in New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Connie Kopelov Papers contains correspondence, writings and speeches, publications, leaflets, notes, clippings, photographs, and other materials, from the mid 1960s to the early 2000s. The bulk of the collection is made up of material from Kopelov's activities in the New York City chapter of the Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), which includes meeting minutes, correspondence, and conference proceedings. Kopelov was also active in multiple community, labor, and women's organizations; most of the materials from these organizations are found in Series III. This collection is rich in material on women's rights in the workforce, in addition to other labor and feminist activism in New York City in the 1970s and 1980s.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 3 series: I) Connie Kopelov Biographical and Activity Files; II) Coalition of Labor Union Women Files; III) Subject Files.
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series. Series IV has not been arranged by an archivist.
Appraisal
Published books found in the library collection were removed.
Separated Material
Connie Kopelov's MA thesis, "Trade Union Women and Women's Rights" (Goddard College, 1974) has been catalogued and placed in the Tamiment Library book collection (HD6079.2.U5 K66 1974a).
An oral history interview with Connie Kopelov (conducted by Debra Bernhardt, 1981) is available at the Tamiment Library in the New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection (OH.001).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Women labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs.; Speeches.; Women labor union members -- New York (N.Y.); Reports.; Correspondence.; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.).; Newsletters.; Minutes (administrative records); Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.). New York City Chapter; Siegel, Phyllis; Kopelov, Connie; Worker's Defense League; Kopelov, Connie; Siegel, Phyllis
- Series I: Connie Kopelov Biographical and Activity Files, 1960-2006
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I, Connie Kopelov Files (1963-1994) consists of Kopelov's correspondence, resumes, speeches, and publications. Also included are materials from Kopelov's 1963 campaign for Democratic District Leader, 4th A.D. North, in New York City. The series contains letters sent to Kopelov from persons representing various organizations such as CLUW, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, and the New York City Council Committee on Women. The series also contains speeches and publications that Kopelov authored and co-authored throughout her career, including histories of CLUW and studies of notable female labor activists.
  - Biographical, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Campaign Committee: Democratic District Leaders, Sep 5, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1994, 2001, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History in the Making: The Formation of the Coalition of Labor Union Women, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications, Undated, 1974-1990, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Resumes, 1960-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speeches and Writings, Undated, 1974-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Coalition of Labor Union Women Files, 1973-1993
  Series II, Coalition of Labor Union Women Files (1974-1993), comprising the bulk of material in the collection, consists of the national CLUW constitution and statement of purpose and papers from national CLUW conferences, as well as minutes, correspondence, leaflets, and programs from the New York City Chapter of CLUW from the years 1974 to 1993. The series also contains CLUW newsletters, both local and national.
  - CLUW: CLUW News, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CLUW Constitution, Dec 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CLUW: East Coast Conference, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CLUW: Executive Board Directory, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CLUW: Founding Conference, Mar 23-24, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - CLUW: National Conference, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CLUW: Statement of Purpose, Structure and Guidelines, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - CLUW Tenth Anniversary Conference, Chicago, IL, Mar 22-25, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Annual Awards Dinner-Dance Program, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Annual Awards Dinner-Dance Program, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Annual Awards Dinner-Dance Program, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: By-Laws, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Calendar, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: CLUW Day Awards Luncheon, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: CLUW Day Celebration, Feb 4, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: CLUW Day Program, Dec 1, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW Conference: "Fighting Back in '82: Skills and Strategies", Apr 3, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW Conference: "Working Women's Awareness Day", May 10, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Domestic Violence Seminar, Apr 14, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Education Committee, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Fifteenth Anniversary Dinner-Dance, Jun 2, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: History, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27A)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: International Women's Day Celebration, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: International Women's Day Committee, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, Undated, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Leaflets, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Minutes and Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Newsletters, 1974-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Photographs and Membership Cards, 1960s, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Photographs, 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Sexual Harassment Panel Discussion, Mar 6, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - New York City Chapter, CLUW: Women and Health Seminar, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - New York City Chapter, New Jersey Chapter, CLUW: Biennial Convention and Educational Training Conference, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Organizing the Unorganized: CLUW sponsored event, Nov 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1971-2005
  Series III, Subject Files (1971-2001) contains materials that Kopelov collected from various community, labor, and women's organizations, including campaign leaflets, information leaflets, photographs, and notes and programs from conferences. Also in this series are news clippings collected by Kopelov, many of them pertaining to CLUW news and activities.
  - Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: Demonstration Against Farah Pants (organized by C.K.), Jan 1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: Newsletter, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Association for Union Democracy: The Women's Project, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bel, Ronny: Crane Operator, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Central Labor Rehabilitation Council of New York, Inc., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Citizen Action of New York, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Citizens for Tax Justice, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Civil Service Technical Guild (AFSCME), Local 375: "Our Mothers-Ourselves", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Clippings, 1973-2002 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Coalition for a Just Supreme Court, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Coalition to Stop U.S. Intervention in the Middle East, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Columbia University School of Social Work: The Workplace Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Contact Sheet, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cornell University: New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Dingell, John: Congressman (Photograph), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference, Jan 19, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference: Correspondence, Dec 1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference: Planning Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference: Program Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference: Songs, Jan 19, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - First New York Trade Union Women's Conference: Speakers, Jan 19, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Housing Justice Campaign, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Institute on Women's History (C.K. participant), Jul 14, 1979-Jul 29, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Institute on Women's History: Kopelov's Notes, Jul 14, 1979-Jul 29, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Institute on Women's History: Photographs, Jul 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Institute on Women's History: Songs, Jul 14, 1979-Jul 29, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - International Association of Machinists, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - International Ladies Garment Workers Union: PACEsetter(Kopelov articles), Undated, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - International Women's Day Celebration, Mar 6, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - International Women's Day Panel (C.K. speaks), Mar 5, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - March for Women's Lives, Apr 5, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Organization for Women, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO, undated, Jul 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New York Coalition of Labor: "The Effect of the Recession on Women Workers", May 18, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - New-York Historical Society: Newsletter, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - New York International Socialists, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - New York Labor Committee in Support of Democracy and Human Rights in El Salvador, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - New York Labor History Association, 1989, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - New York Labor History Association: John Commerford Labor Education Awards (C.K. Honoree), Nov 15, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - New York Labor History Association: Tours, 1997-1998, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - New York Trade Union Women, undated, 1974, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, 1960-1981 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photographs and Ephemera, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Public Employee: Special History Issue, Jul 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reproductive Rights, undated, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE): Lifetime Achievement Awards, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE): Newsletter, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Services and Advocacy for Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, and Transgender Elders (SAGE), Undated, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Trade Union Women and Women Rights, Aug 9, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Trade Union Women's Studies Conference, Nov 14, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - United Farm Workers, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - United Mine Workers of America, Aug 1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - United Nations: March to Abolish Nuclear Weapons, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - United Staff Association of New York University, undated, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Wade, Betsy and Glaubach, Marjorie: "A Woman's Place is in her Union", undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Women for Racial and Economic Equality, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Women's Funding Coalition, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Women Share News: Newsletter, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Workers and Allies: Female Participation in the American Trade Union Movement: Exhibition (C.K. speaks), May 4, 1971-May 9, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Workers Defense League, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Nametags, 1986-1993 (Box 3)
  - CLUW Paperweight, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A007)
- Series IV: 2014 Addendum, 1940s-2011 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Flat-file-folder 2, Box 4)
  The accession includes four audiocassettes, including her talk, "Knowing Our History Gives Us Power: Women in American Labor History", plaques and certificates acknowledging her achievements, photographs, writings, and other ephemera. The materials represent her work with UNITE! (Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees) and her work as an activist for women in the labor movement. These materials include course modules she taught about working women, her writings on influential labor union women for the Encyclopedia of New York State, Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW) ephemera and articles, and her thesis, "Trade Union Women and Women's Rights". The series also includes hagadot, materials from the first New York Trade Women's Conference, photographs from rallies and her going away party in 1967, speeches, and some personal writings. She was also involved in the New York Labor History Association; materials related to her work are also found in this accession.
  This series also contains oversized materials, including a recording of The Inheritance, the soundtrack for the 50th anniversary film of the Amalgamated clothing Workers of America; Labor History Association posters; Coalition of Labor Union Women posters; posters related to the "Don't Buy Farah Pants!" campaign; a marriage equality poster which includes an image of Kopelov and her partner Phyllis Siegel; and a poster with the slogan, "if you want it done right, hire a woman."
- Series V: Accession NPA 1997.025 - Photographs, 1958-1991 (Box 5)